hello my name is Liz and in this lesson
I want to look at the different types of
questions that the examiner might ask
you in IELTS speaking part one now as
you know you need to prepare lots of
different topics so for example family
hobbies going out birthdays but you also
need to prepare for different types of
questions so even though the examiner
will ask you about different topics the
questions are often the same so let's
have a look at some common questions for
IELTS speaking part one so let's take a
look at a common topic and that's the
topic of cooking it is a common topic to
get in speaking part one now you can see
a list of questions here so let's take a
look at these questions more closely
what you can see is that each question
begins with a different question word
and this is very important to understand
about speaking part one because every
topic that you get in speaking part one
can have questions let's start with
these question words so for example how
often do you cook this is looking at
frequency so the number of times you
cook in a week or in a month who usually
does the cooking this is a person so
either you or someone else in your
family where did you learn to cook so
this is a place did you learn to cook in
your own home or was it in a school or
on a course when did you learn to cook
this is for a time so for this you'll
need to give a date or for example 10
years ago or when I was a child how long
have you been cooking another common
question this is about the length of
time so you could say I've been cooking
for six years and that means I
started cooking six years ago and of
course what kind of dishes do you like
this is also a common question so for
example do you like spicy dishes chicken
dishes what kind
so these question words are very
important and you need to listen for
them in the speaking part one test so
that you can give the right information
in your answer and here are more
questions that are very common in IELTS
speaking part one so you can see the
first one which is a can you question
it's very common to get this for any
topic can you swim can you dance
can you cook and you need to answer yes
I can or no I can't and add some more
information also we've got do you like
so this is what you enjoy it could also
be do dislike so listen out for that and
what's your favorite a very common
question what's your favorite book
what's your favorite dish what's your
favorite newspaper it could be any
question like this and again you need to
express the dish that you like most
another one is preferring so this is all
about preferences do you prefer this or
do you prefer this so do you prefer
eating at home or do you prefer eating
out you need to choose one and explain
your preference we've also got do you
usually so this is about your common
habits what you do frequently so do you
usually cook for yourself and you need
to answer yes or no and again add more
information the next one what do you
usually cook this is about what dish so
for example I often cook Chinese food or
I often cook veg
therrien dishes the next one is a do you
ever and this is in the present tense so
this is now so do you ever order food
delivery and you need to say yes or no
and then explain why or give some more
examples and the next one is have you
ever and with this question this is
actually a past tense question so that
means we're looking at what you've done
in the past so have you ever eaten any
food from a foreign country and you can
say yes and you can explain when or what
kind of food it was so again very common
questions you can get in almost any
topic now there are a couple more so
let's look at the last few so here are
the last two types of questions for
IELTS speaking part one this one did you
ever cook when you were a child now it's
very important that you pay attention to
this question because this is a clear
past tense question about your childhood
and of course this is testing your past
tense your grammar so it's very
important that you listen for the tents
in the question because this is a
language test so if you don't give a
past tense answer that might be a
problem and the next question now of
course speaking part one is mostly about
yourself
what do you like what do you prefer can
you when do you what do you is mostly
about yourself but you can also get
questions about people in your country
or about people in general so here we've
got a question why do some people
dislike cooking now please if you get a
question like this don't talk about
yourself this is about other people
so with this question you'll need to
explain why there are people who don't
enjoy cooking well that's all for this
lesson I'll see you
again in another IELTS lesson
you